this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
SE radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
hello everyone this is Priyanka raghwan
for software engineering radio
today we will be discussing Oasis
stands for Zed attack proxy a security
testing tool with our guest Simon
Bennetts Simon is a distinguished
engineer at jit and released zap in 2010
he has worked on nearly every part of
Sap's code base and he has given several
talks and tutorial on zap which are
available on the official documentation
page
you can probably hear a lot of
excitement in my voice because I'm a big
fan of his work so it's great to have
you on the show and welcome thank you
very much thank you for inviting me it's
a pleasure to be here we have done two
episodes on oasp and dynamic application
security testing episode
467 with Kim Carter on Dynamic
application security testing and episode
514 with Vandana Varma on oasp top 10.
so maybe we can start right at the top
Simon and the first question I wanted to
ask you is what is dynamic application
security testing which people keep
talking about and does zap fall under
this category so yes zap is a dynamic
application security testing tool
otherwise known as dast and there's
quite a few different types of security
testing as you well know there's static
application security testing and that's
where you look at the source code and
you know you can see certain there's
types of vulnerabilities you can find
that way zap doesn't work in that way
zap doesn't look at the source code at
all it actually looks at the running
application so this is I wouldn't say
that dast is better than sast or vice
versa they're just different ways of
approaching the same thing what we're
trying to do is find vulnerables in
applications uh zap is focused on web
applications and what zap does it
interacts with the app application via
HTTP https websockets all those web
Technologies so zap does attack your
application if you tell it to it'll only
do what you tell it to do but in some
ways you can think of it like it's
trying to do the same things as a
malicious attacker so somebody who knows
about web vulnerabilities and tries to
attack your application now zap tries
not to do any damage but I have taken
out many websites in the past
unintentionally so we don't try and
delete data from databases but zap can
put quite a lot of strain on websites
and so particularly if they're not used
to a lot of traffic so it can be tricky
so you should we should stress you
should only use that on applications you
have permission to test or that you
yourself own yeah I think yeah that
makes a lot of sense and also a good
warning to our users that definitely try
to make sure that you have permissions
to test what you're producing maybe as a
software engineer it's probably okay to
use app but then make sure it's only on
the dev and
okay the other thing I wanted to ask you
was I was reading somewhere in one of
these blogs that said that zap was
actually born out of a need for testing
an application that you were working on
yeah so can you tell us a little bit
about that sure so my background is
software development so this is in 2009
I was a developer and team leader as a
small team and we were developing an
online application for a ftse 100
company in the UK so that's one of the
top 100 companies
and we knew it was security critical so
we planned around that and we
implemented the service and a couple of
weeks before it was supposed to go live
we got the penetration testers in just
so the whole idea was this was as far as
I was concerned yeah it was a tick in
the boxing you know just to prove we'd
done everything right
it didn't quite work out that way so got
a couple of guys in and you know
explained everything about the service
because I knew yeah they're on our side
we wanted to find any vulnerabilities
before it went live obviously put them
in a room explained everything and you
know let them get on with it and went
back an hour later just to see if I
could explain anything if there's
anything they didn't understand
and I still remember walking into that
room and seeing one of the pen testers
logged into the admin console with my
credentials
they shouldn't have had those they had
he had got super user access to the
service
that was a problem it was actually worse
than that because although it wasn't
actually a vulnerability in the service
I developed or my team developed that
actually cracked the single sign-on
service for the whole company this is a
ftse 100 company that cracked the single
sign-on service in one hour
this was a bit of a wake-up call is at
that point I thought okay this week is
not gonna go the way I hoped and at the
end of the week it seemed like a car
crash the report seemed awful I now know
it wasn't as bad as it appeared and I've
delivered worse reports myself now but
it did not feel good at the time so you
know I just kind of had to I felt
particularly bad and I decided to take
stock you know I was a developer and I
knew I was good at developing web
services I could develop the services
that did what they're supposed to do
they were performance they were
maintainable they clearly weren't secure
enough so I it was time for me to learn
about security one of the pen testers
had told me about a wasp which I'm
afraid to say at that time I hadn't
heard of and if any of your listeners
haven't heard about it's the open web
application security project
actually it's open worldwide application
security project I don't think it's just
web anymore so I hadn't heard about wasp
looked at a wasp and they've got
something called the top 10
um most common risks to web applications
so that covers things like your
cross-site scripting and SQL injection
so I've read all that but when it comes
down to it I'm a developer and I like
playing with things I don't learn as
well from reading stuff so I decided
what I was going to do is I'd find some
tools to help me and I'm a big fan of
Open Source so it's hard to go down the
open source route and I didn't really
want to go to management and say you've
got to spend loads of money on tools and
I kind of wanted to I wanted a tool that
allowed me to do several things one I
wanted to actually use it to run on my
own software every night so I wouldn't
get embarrassed by the pen testers again
but I also wanted to learn from it so I
didn't just want something that you
press a button and it magically did
everything I wanted to see what was
going on underneath so I wanted a tool I
could learn from and I've always had
side projects and I thought well maybe
you know this time this would be good
time to get open source maybe it's an
open source web security project I could
get involved in
so I have had a round looking for a
maintained open source web security tool
and at that time there were none
absolutely zero and that felt wrong to
me but it is what was what it was so
what I did was I found some tools that
have been that were no longer maintained
there was an almost tool called Web
Scarab which I didn't really get on with
it was quite complicated and didn't work
the way it just didn't seem to gel with
me but there was another tool called
Paris proxy which is quite nice quite
simple I started playing around with
that and cut a long story short I ended
up forking it and creating zap from that
fog wow that's a great story which leads
to my next question so was the tool then
built with an audience that was only for
developers or is it okay also for pen
distance yeah so I mean when I released
it I was definitely much um a developer
and didn't consider myself a security
person so there was an old security list
called Bug track so I posted a message
on there saying that you know I was
releasing this tool it was a fork of
Paris proxy it was really I the tagline
was actually the security tool for
developers so I was definitely going for
that but I said to you know maybe some
Security Professionals might find it
useful as well but I really I didn't
feel I had the cheek to
say it was a suitable tool for Security
Professionals when I wasn't one myself
and we kept that tagline for quite a
while until I started going to Eros
events and Pen testers kept on coming up
to me and saying hey it's not just for
developers you know we use it as well so
after a few years we kind of decided we
had to drop that tagline and you know
we've kind of realized over the years
that a lot of security people use zap
and I suppose in the years I've probably
had to claim I'm a security person now
myself as well as well as being a
developer okay great so the audience is
both pen testers as well as developers
and anybody with an interest in testing
exactly and it we've made things a bit
difficult for ourselves really because
our audience goes from people who are
who know nothing about security they
could be developers they could be
students doesn't really matter if you're
technical but interested in security
then web security then zap is a tool for
you but it goes all the way up to
hardcore pen testers who know exactly
what they want and probably use multiple
a whole range of tools but sap will be
one of them and you know they need to
understand the strength some weaknesses
of each tool and to use them as
appropriate so it's difficult to keep
everyone happy we can't but we do our
best that's actually true the line that
you just said making everyone happy
that's really tough but one thing about
zap is what is the thing that you think
that differentiates you from the other
tools out there in the market and why
are you still open source
oh good questions so I mean one of the
biggest things I think is being open
source there are a few other open source
web security tools but nothing quite
like sap
so you know we're open source we're
Community Based so we want anyone to be
able to get involved
so that for me is a key differentiator
but we know and we know we do compete
with commercial tools and some of those
commercials also have a lot of people
working on them a lot more than we do
but I still think zap has some
significant strengths I think in
automation we're probably the best Das
tool out there and our API is incredible
it's you know you can do pretty much
anything via the API and our scripting
capabilities are second to none as well
so you can essentially rewrite zap on
the Fly virtually we know that a lot
that you know some power users make
heavy use of the scripting features
because zap is open source we've got
nothing to hide so the scripting
interface can access all of the zap
classes it can access all the data
structures we consider that the code
belongs to community and the data
belongs to whoever's using zap so you
should be able to get hold of anything
you want to and do whatever you like
with zap and if you can't let us know
and we'll learn it make sure you can
okay I think that brings me on to my my
one last question before we jump into
zap oh that the thing with the the point
that you made about apis and
extensibility that makes it easier to
lack of a better way of explaining
shifting left which I don't like now
nowadays but then anyway shifting left
security do you have like a story which
might say that somebody use zap and then
you know they went from this usual
waterfall model that you've talked about
in was it 2009 that you said to Now
using zap and everything is like you
know they test it immediately because of
all the hooks that you know I wish I had
more stories one of the problems is as
an open source tool anyone can download
it and use it and they don't have to
tell us so not many people tell us about
how they use app we do have a few user
stories success stories on the website
but if anyone out there has got stories
about how you use app would love to hear
them I did hear talking on extensibility
recently I heard from someone on the
Elvis board about a very large Bank in
the United States who tested all of the
Dust tools out there all the main ones
including all the main commercial tools
and it couldn't get any of the
commercial tools working with their
application because of some technical
reasons and zap was the only one they
could actually get working and that
didn't work out of the box but it came
down to scripting because we've got such
an extensive scripting capability they
were able to actually change that
scripts app so that it could handle
their particular case so that's you know
one of the biggest banks in America can
only use zap to scan its web
applications at the moment that's
impressive to hear and I guess the
question I wanted to ask you now is like
considering it's open source and how do
you have this shared vision and team
cohesiveness and to produce something
that was constantly like every time you
look at the zap Mark Case there are
frequent updates how do you manage that
with difficulty so we have a small core
team there's four of us I think it's we
probably it's only the equivalent of two
people working full-time on zap really
but you know we've got a lot of other
contributors so and one thing we're
trying to do now is trying to work out
how to actually resource that better
because we need more people working on
zap so we're trying to get we know a lot
of commercial companies are actually
wrapping zap in commercial products so
I'd love them to contribute back more
some of them already do but a company I
work for jit they're sponsoring my work
ons app which is brilliant and would
love more the companies that use app
more of them to actually do something
similar so you know would love people to
be sponsored to work on zap I would love
to raise more money so we could pay
people to work on zap there has been
some controversy within obos we're
trying to convince our was to make it
easier to focus more on funding projects
but when it comes down to it I think
raising money has never been one of our
strengths I'm afraid okay so more than
the technical problems I think it's the
C would it be fair to say that funding
is one of the challenges with
maintaining an open source project
definitely if you need a significant
number of a significant amount of effort
it's something you can't do in your
spare time I started off doing in zap in
my spare time and I wasn't able to get
very far and luckily Mozilla came along
and sponsored my work and now Jitter
sponsoring it but we really need people
being able to spend a decent amount of
time a couple of the zap core teams you
know most of the rest of the zap core
team do it in their spare time which is
incredible but we need you know people
to be able to dedicate more of their
time to zap one last question I wanted
to know is how did zap become like a
flagship project or is it because of the
kind of contributions that is there on
yet how does that work oh good question
I mean I think I'm not sure what the
process was at the time I know what the
process is now because I'm actually on
the iOS projects committee so the idea
is that projects can request to go up
but I think it's incubator then Labs
then production is that the labels we
use Flagship is something different so
Flagship is something that is much more
significant to a wasp it's not just
saying it's a great project it's also
saying it's a great project but it's key
to the direction of O wasp so I think
that is a bored decision to decide to
actually make a project Flagship I
wasn't involved in the decision at the
time but I think because sap stuck
around so long and because zap became so
well known and so widely used it
actually has such a very beneficial
effect for it on our wasp that's good to
hear so now actually I'd like to switch
gears and go into a little bit on the
tool itself for our audience which is
predominantly a lot of software
Engineers but right now with someone
like me was coming a little bit with the
security background we also have that
group so let's talk a little bit on the
of two versions of Zap that you have you
have like a desktop version and also a
zap demon CLI so can you tell us how
that came about sure so I mean it's
actually only one version of that but
you can run it in different ways so
originally that was just a desktop tool
and that's because that's what Paris was
Paris proxy which I thought originally
but my whole idea I think as I've
initially said what I wanted originally
was a tool I could automate to test mine
applications so having a a command line
version was one of the things I wanted
to work on pretty early on so the
command line version got implemented
quite early on but since then we found
that people you know there are lots of
different use cases for the way people
want to run zap so we've got a quite a
wide range of options now we've still
got the desktop so you can have this
swing UI that are JavaScript UI that you
can interact with and we still recommend
that's a good way to learn about that
because you can then see what's going on
if you want to debug it and I think it's
much easier you can see all the requests
and responses you can play with things
interactively so the desktop version is
still very important we have a demon
mode as you mentioned so we can put zap
into the background no UI and then we've
got a very thorough API which allows you
to do nearly as much as you can do from
the desktop GUI not quite but nearly
then we have the automation framework
and the automation framework is a bit
different because it allows you to
control zap from one yaml file so it has
a series of jobs and those jobs can do
things like running the spiders running
active scanner importing API definitions
kind of the things we expect we think
people would want to do most frequently
in automation
so you can create this yaml file and you
can actually that works in both the
desktop and from the command line so you
can play around with it get it working
the desktop and then save it and run it
from the command line
we also have some what we call package
scans and they basically run zap in
specific ways well actually those are
actually Python scripts which were
migrating to the automation framework
but they only run in Docker so we have
Docker images and that's where the
package scans lived now the automation
framework will run in Docker one from
the command line it isn't dependent on a
container so the automation framework is
a bit more flexible in that way and we
also have the heads up display which is
another way of running zap and this is
where we actually add controls to your
field of vision so we actually decorate
the browser with zap controls and
information so you can see what's going
on while you're focusing on your
application and the Heart actually works
both in Daemon and desktop mode as well
so we have all of those options yeah I'm
going to add some show notes to the
hardware so that people can actually
look at a visual but one of the things I
was curious when I was working on the
heart was were you doing it so that you
know like in the future maybe you would
blow up this onto a big screen and have
one of those virtual glasses and then
you go and point on something I mean I'm
just asking just curious so because I
would almost look yeah it almost looks
like you would do something like that I
am actually a big fan of virtual reality
so I've got my Quest 2 behind me here
and I have actually used zap in virtual
reality but I think that was just
connecting to a desktop so one of the
problems with the browsers in VR at the
moment you don't get as much control
over them and you can't it's there's not
an easy way to proxy them through
security tools like zap so it is
something I'd love to have a play with
but technically it's quite tricky and I
mean they're often solutions to these
things but they can take a while and
it's probably not high enough anywhere
near high enough of my priority list for
me to be able to play that but yeah I
would love to be able to use zap in VR
and have the controls floating around
the browser there that would be
brilliant yeah
so maybe any listeners on the show who
have Graphics experience should probably
contribute to that thing yeah definitely
and I've played around a bit with webvr
as well and I was wondering whether we
could actually have some information
from zapcon is itself a web server so we
do have you know web interface web VR
interface to zap but integrating that
with a browser and actually seeing what
you know the user sees is technically
quite tricky okay
we had actually done an episode 474 on
Fast testing or not done by me but
another host and they talked a lot about
how fuzzing is very important for doing
security testing or even you know normal
testing and I do see that we have a
fuzzer in zap so can you talk a little
bit about this fuzzing support that zap
provides sure so one of the things with
web application test security testing is
it's always a balance so you can throw
random stuff or loads and loads of
potentially bad things to application
and see what happens but it takes a long
time particularly if you think that web
applications typically have a lot of
things you can attack because you have
URL parameters you have form parameters
you have headers you've got web sockets
there's loads of potential things and so
people often say that Das tools like zap
take a long time and they can take a
long time because there's so much to do
so what we typically do with zap is we
have what we call Scan rules and we have
passive scandals which just look at
things and spot potential problems
without actually interacting with the
application then we have the active
scanner and the active scan rules and
these will actually attack the
application and what we do is we quite
fine grain control over what those rules
can attack so you can tune it to be what
you want but if you turn everything on
then that will attack quite a few things
so in general what we try and do is we
try and do very targeted attacks so we
try and so for example for cross-site
scripting what we'll try and do is
inject a safe token send it to Safe
token across and see it's reflected in
the website if it's reflected there then
we've got more of a chance so we'll then
we'll we'll look at the context within
the HTML where it's reflected and try
and break out of those contexts so we
can actually run some JavaScript so we
can actually do we can kind of focus
quite quickly onto potential problems
and we try not to make too many requests
that aren't actually useful or don't
appear to be useful from an automated
side
so we don't call what we do what our
active scanner of fuzzer because it's
very targeting what it does however we
do have a fuzzer as you mentioned and
this is for us it's a very manual
process because if we know how to detect
potential vulnerabilities then we put
those rules into we codify that as part
of the scan rules but we know we can't
cope with everything and applications
are very specific and a security
professional might well be looking for
some very strange Behavior some unusual
things so what we have is a fuzzer and
with that a pen tester can select one
particular request and then they can
select exactly which characters they
want to change and there's a whole
series of rules so you can you can
specify exactly what the payloads are
you can generate payloads now you can
get payloads from a file you can write
scripts the payloads you can put in
processes so you process every message
every payload it is very very flexible
but it is very much a manual process so
and that's one thing I mentioned the API
allows you to do most things it doesn't
allow you to do fuzzing at the moment we
do plan to add the API to fuzzing but
it's complicated and it's one of the
harder ones to automate okay
and there was a lot of stuff you told us
there so let me just ask you one more
question to summarize what he said so
you said that you do have us one piece
which is of course the fuzzle which you
can do for more sort of testing from a
pen tester's perspective and check
particular Parts with some kind of
complicated inputs maybe whereas you
have the active scanner which you said
which also does this thing for you like
for free like so if I didn't know how to
use the fuzzer I would go in and use
this active scan exactly yeah so what
we're trying to do is make sure that
this app is as easy to use as possible
for people who are new to security
tricky because a lot of security
concepts are non-intuitive we do weird
stuff in security so it is a little bit
tricky but we try to make it as easy as
possible we try to make sure that
newcomers can get started but there's
hidden depths where you can do a lot
more with zap as you learn
okay
one of the other things I wanted to ask
Scott
about the active and the passive scan I
remember once we had a story that had
actually spoken to one of the developers
on my team and asked them to try using
zap and I think they had just blindly
used it on the app and I think it just
piped out the entire Dev database so
like they were committed me up what
happened you asked us to use this and
it's like just deleted all our things
the thing that I wanted to ask is that
there are two options right there is
there an option to do something like a
passive passively test the system yeah
so I mean zap does what you tell it to
do so if you don't tell it to attack
anything it won't attack anything but we
are also aware that people can be
nervous with security tools so we have
what we call modes and we have a safe
mode and if you put zap in safe mode it
won't allow you to any bad things so zap
can actually be very useful for testing
things on production sites you might
actually want to see what requests and
responses are being made you might I
mean I've used that for debugging before
it's particularly useful when you're not
sure what request being made by
JavaScript libraries or the mic so we
can put zap in safe mode and it won't do
anything bad at all there then we have
protected mode and protected mode is
just the same as safe mode unless you
actually tell zap you want to attack
something so zap has this idea of
contexts and context can mean different
things but basically you know you could
think of it like an application so you
add your application to a context you
say it's in scope then zap will allow
you to attack things in that context
that application but won't allow you to
attack anything else so protected mode
is probably a good one for a lot of
people we have the standard mode which
allows you to do everything and I'm
afraid that's what I use all the time
but obviously I know how zap works so I
I know not to attack things when I
shouldn't do we actually have an attack
mode as well and that is where the way
we really recommend you use zap is you
explore the application first then you
start the active scanner we actually
have this option where we put an attack
mode and as soon as you actually say
something is in scope then zap will
attack it and essentially it follows you
around so as you discover more things
zapple attack it so if so you've got a
large application and you want to focus
on one particular part of it if you use
the spider one of the spiders it'll be
very difficult to restrict zap to that
functionality whereas you can put it in
if you explore the application manually
and put an attack mode then you can
basically just invoke whatever
functionality you want to test from the
browser and zap will only attack that
functionality okay
and once you're finished with the scan
what are the results that one would get
does it just provide a list of
exceptions with endpoints and severities
so we provide a lot of information as
much information as we can and so that
will include obviously the vulnerability
we'll show you the request and response
if we've got any evidence it will be
there the payload we used there'll be a
solution in there there'll be a
description there'll be links to other
resources we try and provide as much
information as possible we tag things
like the different oh what's top 10
categories and web application security
guide categories we have a report
sorting add-on which allows you to
generate reports in a whole range of
formats so they could be HTML PDF Json
XML and that's actually very extensible
so we use a Java Library called time
Leaf so you can create your own reports
you don't need to be a programmer we've
got you know all of our templates are
Written In Time Leaf so you can actually
it's just to kind of Mark up language
really so you can create your own
reports we know people have done that
but we do have another add-on which
integrates with bug trackers as well so
you can actually go down that route as
well if you want to if you want to
automatically update a bug tracker
there's also this thing in GitHub right
now this called this security tab right
which has this with GitHub Advanced
security where you can see all I think
there's a format called serif for yeah
so is that also something you are should
a potential person use this timely frame
is that what you said timely and then
okay just check I think we have the
serif format I'm just going to look on
the website now
just to see so we actually have so all
of the add-ons and all of the alerts are
on the website and yes we have a serif
Jason report now as well and okay one
thing I've got to mention is you can
actually run zap in GitHub actions and
the GitHub actions will I think they
raise GitHub issues rather than the
security alerts at the moment but you
can raise issues and track your
potential vulnerabilities that way as
well okay okay that's good to know and
picking up on that I think a few years
back I remember I used to work for an
organization that was using Jenkins and
then for CI and then I obviously
integrated Zap for that and then after
some time they went on to another tool
called Argo and yeah again that was very
easy for me to integrate one of the
exercise that since I did these two
exercises of course I wrote a Blog about
it and stuff and I found that it was
very easy to integrate almost any sort
of CI tool with zap so when you're
building a system is that what you're
always thinking about the ease of
integration with like absolutely
anything like is that a bit
mind-boggling when you're designing
something because there's so much out
there yeah that's actually very
important to us so I mean obviously we
think zap is important but we are very
aware that zap is not an overall
solution it is not doing everything for
everyone and we couldn't do that it's
better we have for tools focused on
particular things so zap is focused on
task scanning and we know that people
will want to integrate that findings
they want to interact with sap you might
want to feed information from one tool
into zap so having zap as a good citizen
is very important so we always think
about ways that we're trying to think
about different ways tools can interact
with zap without being a you know think
about specific tools we want to make
sure zap is easy to run from the command
line you can access as much
functionality by the API as possible and
that we allow zapdata to be accessed in
as many ways as possible so playing well
with other tools whether they're
commercial open source or whatever or
custom ones that people write for
specific purposes that is a very
important thing and that's something we
always bear in mind so if someone adds a
new feature and they don't add an API or
some option like that then that would be
picked up in the review and be like oh
could you you know put this in because
we know that's important to a lot of
people and that brings me to another a
point there was a controversial topic a
few days back where they talked about
when you are you use any of these clean
code Concepts and you have a lot of
modifiability or extensibility then
there's also something that affects your
performance and I think the person would
written it was talking more in terms of
performance so and that's one thing that
just struck me while I was chatting with
you now how does this affect your zap
performance how fast would it be to run
a test if it's a part of your CI setup I
mean that is one problem with dust tools
because there's so much you know we talk
about the whole application there's so
much to test typically so tools like zap
you often think a lot of people think
they can take some time to run and if
you're testing the whole application
that's very true when I was working in
Mozilla that's why I developed what we
call the Baseline scan where we
basically do a very quick crawl of the
application and just passively scan it
that typically finishes in a couple of
minutes so that can be very quick but
it's also zap is very very flexible so
zap doesn't understand source code but
if you're or static analyzer understands
source code and can map that source code
to endpoints then you could get your
cicd system to tell zap that to only
attack the endpoints that are affected
if you can do that then zap will vary
very fast if we're attacking a couple of
URLs even with all of the scan rules
enabled it will be quick so it's very
much a question of how you drive zap and
that's something unfortunate outside of
our control because zap isn't a static
Source analyzer and is never going to be
there's too many different types of Dev
Stacks out there but if your static
analyzer or static code can tell zap
which URLs are affected then you can get
zap to actually just attack those URLs
so Zappa is very very flexible it's just
a question of how you drive it
okay so if you were to run it as a part
of our Ci or process then maybe you have
to use one of those Baseline scans to do
which to something under a minute
oh yeah I said unless you can actually
work out which URL is affected if you
can do that okay then you can really tap
up and we also have we know speed is
very important so we've got other things
things like technology so you can
actually but by default zap assumes that
well it's Black Box testing it doesn't
know what's out there but a lot of the
rules are specific to particular
operating systems or types of technology
and that is actually the rules
understand that so if you tell us that
you're not using an Oracle database
using MySQL then zap will just use the
MySQL rules and it won't use the Oracle
once that's actually I've done some
tests and that can really speed tap up
if you turn up all the technology it's
actually significantly quicker obviously
if you're using that technology you need
to turn those things on but yeah you can
there's a lot of ways of speeding zap up
without actually sacrificing the
effectiveness that's good to know and I
think that also brings me back to
another a question that I saw that I was
thinking about when I was researching
you just now told us that zap can only
be used for web application testing but
I do see Zapped running on I think
there's some tests for running on
Raspberry Pi so is that like the vision
that you want to support like say iot
and like smart devices if they support
web protocols yeah we want terms that
cope with anything which uses web
protocols really so yeah we've got zap
running on Raspberry Pi the performance
isn't too bad with the modern ones to be
honest and we know people use sap for
mobile testing as well that's not
something I've really got involved in
but they're you know we've there's some
articles online we're trying to link to
those so we want zap to be as useful to
as many people as possible iot isn't
really my thing but we definitely want
this app to work well in those
environments and finally before I move
on to the next section since we talked a
little bit about the manual and
automated scanner right which is there
uh what would be the use case 4C and
automated versus a manual would I start
with automated when I if I didn't know
about the application and then go to a
manual mode yeah I mean the to do manual
testing you have to it helps to know a
bit about security and what you're
supposed to do if you don't know what
you're looking for or how to find it
then it's kind of tricky particularly
because a lot of web vulnerabilities are
kind of weird they're not intuitive so
you know a lot of the manual features in
zap we're kind of thinking it would be
web Security Professionals using them
but you've got to be aware that you know
so I mean it's definitely the case
having a pen test experience pen tester
testing your application manually is
much more effective than an automated
scan however it's also much more
expensive so when I was at Mozilla we
would commission a couple of pen tests a
year and on different services and we
had a lot of services so we'd only test
a couple of them every year and we're
talking I mean there's like 40 to 80 000
dollars for one or two weeks work so you
know if you are you've got a lot of
services that's a lot of money and you
can't do it all the time but
vulnerabilities can be added at any
point
so the advantage of a tool like zap is
you can actually run it overnight you
can run it every day and it will not
pick up all the vulnerabilities but it
will pick up some key ones and if you
start getting some vulnerabilities on a
service that could be a good indication
that you're to get some manual pen
testers in as well but you'll also find
that using zap means you get more value
from your pen tests when I was at
Mozilla I often ran the pen tests or the
interaction of the companies doing the
pen tests it was great to see them come
in all confidence and after a couple of
days
they hadn't found any serious
vulnerabilities and then they started
working really hard pen testers are only
human so if they can find easy stuff
they're not going to put as much effort
in if they can find trivial stuff which
they may well be finding with tools like
zap then they've got other things to do
you know they can focus on other stuff
so you know you won't get as much value
whereas if you find the easy stuff then
that's when you get much more value out
of your pen testers and it's also great
you know it's really useful if you find
out early on that say a particular
developer is interesting vulnerabilities
or team then that's where you'd start
looking at getting more training for
these people you know it's finding stuff
as early as possible and finding out the
causes of you know how did this happen
is it you know a lack of training do you
need different Frameworks do you need
you know there's a whole range of things
you should be looking at but finding
potential vulnerabilities as early as
possible is much more cost effective so
I think a lot that really rings on uh
very well because I think a lot of the
big attacks that we've seen in the news
is because of the simpler wasp top 10
vulnerabilities which cause a lot of
millions of dollars in Damages so yeah
finding the low hanging fruits maybe are
the ones that happen often and then
trying to do the pen test in a more
targeted way would be a good that's good
advice definitely yeah the next question
I'm asking is a bit interesting in the
sense that today it's the world of AI
powered buddies and AI power PR tools
what is the risk of maintaining an open
source tool to scan for security
vulnerabilities so tomorrow you might
have somebody adding some malicious code
and then of course that gets you know
susceptible to these supply chain
attacks and a lot of the clients get
infected because they've got that and
then you've got a EI powered party
that's also reviewing the code or
something so it is so what's what do you
think about that kind of a scenario how
zap cope with that AI is a fascinating
topic and I think you know a lot of
people are going to get a lot of benefit
from using AI particularly you know
filling out you know kind of framework
code it will speed people up but I think
the people who use it most effectively
will be the people who know what they're
doing and I think there's a real danger
in people who don't know as much using
AI to generate code particularly if it's
trained on code on the internet because
there's a lot of vulnerabilities out
there and so I think there's a very
significant chance that AI will code
generated code will accidentally
introduce vulnerabilities and it's also
possible to poison it so that it'll
deliberately introduce vulnerabilities
and if people are using it with less
knowledge there's less chance of those
vulnerabilities being picked up so
there's a lot of benefits but there's a
lot of dangers as well and the whole AI
thing where there seems to be a big
mistake in that we're mixing the control
with the data so what it means is you
can actually tell the AI systems chat
gbt whatever what to do but the data it
works on can then change what happens
and how the tool works and that is
really dangerous so there's some
fundamental problems here and I'm not
saying you shouldn't use AI systems to
help you but you have to be aware that
it it's very risky and I think we'll see
some significant vulnerabilities
introduced in this way so how will zap
actually combat those kind of problems
uh suppose somebody gives a market in
the marketplace produces something that
introduces malicious code in the snap
Marketplace so every change that's made
to zap is reviewed by two of the core
team so we will we've got two
experienced people who will be checking
the code and if even doing something a
little bit strange then that's when
would dig deeper so you know if somebody
tried to introduce some malicious code
we would aim to find that as you know
hopefully that wouldn't get through the
review due process we do static analysis
on zap code as well so we're using many
of the security tools we possibly can
but I think in this case the manual
review and it's not just a case of that
we can't see any obvious vulnerabilities
the code has to be sensible and be doing
sensible things it is doing weird things
for no readily apparent reason that
would make us suspicious we want zap to
be as maintainable as possible and as
secure as possible and we're aware that
people could accidentally introduce
vulnerabilities or they could try and
deliberately introduce vulnerabilities
so if there's any code that looks
suspicious that's when we'd dig a lot
deeper so yeah I think that the manual
review process for zap is the the key
thing for us so the humans will stop the
AI generated code hopefully in zap yes
that's the idea okay okay that's good to
know and it's interesting when you say
that you run a lot of your security
tooling
tooling slab code base
or a desktop app how do you do the
dynamic testing you use up to test up we
have use app to test that but yeah as a
desktop tool or even as a kind of
dynamic tool it's harder to test but we
do static static analysis on pull
requests and regularly as well but yeah
the dynamic side we have used that and
we do have a bug Bounty so here and we
add you know we know security
researchers have definitely played
around with zap so if you can get a
remote code execution on zap that's a
thousand dollars and we've paid out a
three times I think for that okay
so the next question is what is the
process if someone wants to start
contributing to zap can you explain that
to our listeners I'll obviously add some
information on whatever you see to the
show notes at the end yeah so zap is a
community tool it always has been I was
originally looking for a community-based
tool so I could join couldn't find that
and end up creating that Community
myself so in some ways I think it's
easier to for a small team to maintain
any tool on their own without anyone
else get involved the zap team really
believes it's important for people to be
able to get involved the options for
working on a world-class tool like zap
is really useful and really important
and we've had a lot of students work on
zap and we've actually got student Hall
of Fame a lot of students have worked on
zap through Google summer of code and
other projects but you don't have to be
just go via Google summer of code anyone
can get involved in zap we want people
to get involved and we'll be very happy
to help you we have a zap contributing
guide so just go onto the zap website
zaproxy.org and we'll put links in I'm
sure but then yeah there's a long guide
which explains all the things you can do
to help help us with zap and it's not
just coding obviously coding's a main
thing but there's documentation Alice
using Zapped test things writing blog
posts there's a million things you can
do and we try and make it as easy as
possible for people to get involved we
do know as a security tool it's
something developers might be nervous
getting involved in but I mean I was a
developer and I learned security quite a
few of us have learned security build
working on zap Rick who's won the core
team was the security guy and learned
how to develop by working on zap has had
loads of students who actually made some
really key implemented some key features
in zap so we know a lot anyone can make
really useful contributions so we'd like
to get in touch having a look at the
contributing guide but also just ping me
I'm easy to find online and we'll
include those details so get in touch
and we'll we'll see what we can do how
we can help you okay that's great and uh
finally before I end there is a question
on web application data leakage problems
I know you said that essentially you can
use zap to test data problems or I mean
you can use zap with your own data but
suppose I had a an example where I have
a data leakage problem and I want to
figure out if it's really an issue like
I know that my application has a data
leakage problem could I use Zap for that
would I just as a novice person like or
should I be looking at some apis that
with particular calls being made to the
database find that and then try to use
Zap for that or how could I find out if
my app has a data leakage problem if
it's kind of usually a blended approach
is best now one thing with sap we've got
some passive scan rules which will
attempt to detect data leaks they're
typically reported as either
informational or low but it's still but
things like credit card numbers we spot
numbers that look like valid credit
cards and user information so we will
report information like that so one of
the key things for any tool like zap is
how effectively you explore your
application now the most effective way
for an application designed for humans
is to get the human to do that so you
can actually start this app you can
launch browsers from zap and then you
can explore your application manually
and if zap spots any data that we know
to be interesting being leaked then that
will be reported to you and if there are
particular things you're looking for
that we're not looking for then you can
create your own scandals so you can
create your own passive scan rules you
don't have to be a programmer to do that
I mean obviously some programming
knowledge helps but you can write those
things in scripts and we've got a load
of example scripts in the community
scripts repo so we've got examples of
how to do these things so you can
actually write some custom rules in a
scripting language of your choice we
support quite a few which looks for
things that are very specific to your
industry to your application to your
company
and then as long as you explore the
application effectively zap will report
those things
if you don't have time to explore it
manually we can explore it with we've
got two spiders one a traditional spider
which is very fast but can't handle
modern applications as well and we've
got an Ajax spider which launches
browsers to handle the Ajax side the
modern applications and clicks on things
we can also import API definitions so
whether it's soap open API graphql all
these kind of things we can import so if
you can explore your application
effectively then zap will tell you what
data gets leaked so what I'm hearing is
if you tweak zap in the right way then
you'll be able to find out if you have a
data leakage problem or not yeah well I
mean we'll look for some standard things
but if it's not standard then yeah it's
very easy to extend zap to look for
whatever you want okay okay that's great
and I have actually forgotten to ask
this question but one of the things that
you said is of course you don't have to
only check the UI part of it you can
also check apis as well right so having
that example option yeah that's pretty
powerful yeah and I mean if you're using
some weird format we don't recognize
then you can still just you know if you
can proxy another tool through zap then
you can get that to invoke your API or
do whatever you need to do so you know
we try to import support all the
standard API definitions if there's
somebody we don't support you think we
should then let me know but you can just
proxy any other tool through zap as well
I think it's quite a comprehensive list
of questions that I've asked you and
we'll find out later how it goes finally
how does one find you are you would we
have to go on the website or are you
wouldn't what I want to say one of these
social networking websites like Twitter
are you like active there or yes very
much so so on the zap website we have a
community then a team link and the
Zapped core team are there and links to
all of our social networks I use the
username sign on psii non so that's what
I am on Twitter on GitHub all these
other things so you should be able to
find if you can't find me then you're
really not trying very hard but we'll
include some of the key links yeah I'll
definitely add a link to your Twitter
handle and of course GitHub as well so
it's been great having you on the show
Simon thanks for coming is there
anything else that you want to tell us
before we sign off
just thank you again for having me it's
been a pleasure talking to you and you
know we do want people to get involved
so you know if you want to get involved
please do just get in touch and we are
looking for companies to support this
app in the same way that jit does so if
you're using zap company using zap and
you're interested in helping us out
making zap even better then please get
in touch with me as well thank you this
is Priyanka raghavan for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]
foreign